Guide to the Henry Raup Wagner Collection of Texas Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Henry Raup Wagner Collection of Texas manuscripts
1707-1847
WA MSS S-339
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.5
(5 boxes)
Letters, including several from or pertaining to Stephen F. Austin, official correspondence and documents, degrees, expedientes and reports,recording the history and development of Mexico's northeastern frontier from 1707-1847. Most of the collection concerns Texas, but there are also important documents concerning Louisiana and New Mexico.
Wagner, Henry R. (Henry Raup), 1862-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Henry Raup Wagner, 1919.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Other portions of Wagner's Texas manuscripts have been cataloged separately. They include the Wagner Collection of Texas and Coahuila Land Grants and papers of Jean Louis Berlandier and of Philip Nolan.
Scope and Contents
The Henry Raup Wagner Collection of Texas Manuscripts contains letters, including several from or pertaining to Stephen F. Austin, official correspondence and documents, decrees, "expedientes" and reports, recording the history and development of Mexico's northeastern frontier from 1707-1847. Most concern Texas, but the collection also includes documents concerning Louisiana, New Mexico, the Provincias Internas and the Estados Internos de Oriente. Researchers should note that spelling variations as found on the original documents are maintained in the finding aid, so "jefe" may appear as "gefe", "Bexar" as "Bejar", etc. When searching for specific terms, this should be taken into account. The original documents are accompanied by a series of typed translations, prepared by John V. Clay and Alan Probert, of the letters and documents concerning Juan Davis Bradburn.
Elections -- Texas; Indians of North America -- Commerce -- Louisiana; Indians of North America -- Commerce -- Texas; Indians of North America -- Texas; Land grants -- New Spain -- Provincias Internas; Land grants -- Texas; Livestock -- Mexico -- Coahuila (State); Mexican War, 1846-1848; Missions -- Texas; Louisiana -- History -- 1803-1865; Louisiana -- History -- To 1803; Mexico -- History -- Wars of Independence, 1810-1821; Nacogdoches (Tex.); Natchitoches (La.); New Mexico -- History -- To 1848; Palafox (Tex.) -- History; Provincias Internas (New Spain) -- History; Texas -- Boundaries -- United States; Texas -- History -- To 1846; Texas -- Politics and government -- To 1846; United States -- Boundaries -- Texas; Public officers -- Mexico; Austin, Stephen F. (Stephen Fuller), 1793-1836; Bradburn, Juan Davis, 1787-1842; Mier y Teran, Manuel de; Músquiz, Ramón, approximately 1797-; Ramos Arizpe, Miguel, 1775-1843; Estados Internos de Oriente (Mexico). Comandante General (1829-1832: Mier y Teran); Estados Internos de Oriente (Mexico). Comandante General (1834-1835: Cos)
- Original Documents, Dates 1707-1847; Series I; 1.5; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The original documents are arranged chronologically.
  - Mexico. (Viceroyalty) Viceroy, 1702- 1709 (Albuquerque)
    - LS to Pedro de Aguirre, Mexico., 1707 Sep 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      3 p. 22 cm. Aguirre was captain of the Compania Volante del Rio de Norte.
  - Coahuila, Mexico. Governor, 1709 (Padilla)
    - Copy of proceedings of Gov. Padilla on royal cedula requiring seizure of property of Portuguese nationals., 1709 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      5 p. 32 cm.
  - Mexico. (Viceroyalty) Viceroy, 1716- 1722 (Zuniga)
    - Despatch ordering military escort for two missionaries going to Texas, Mexico., 1722 Jul 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      3 p. 32 cm.
  - Spain. Laws, statutes, etc.
    - Copia de la real cedula sobre oficios vendibles y renunciables., 1733 Mar 13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      2 p. 32 cm.
  - Mexico. (Viceroyalty) Viceroy, 1734- 1740, (Vizarron)
    - LS to Blas de la Garzo Falcon, Governor of Coahuila and de Ecoy y Musquiz, Capt. of Presidio de Rio Grande, Mexico., 1735 Oct 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      20 p. 32 cm. Concerning orders for founding mission at Peyot and Presidio Sacramento de Rio Grande. With the letter are bound copies of the orders, official statements of their execution, diary of the expedition to the new presidio and a list of members of the expedi- tion.
  - Mexico (Viceroyalty) Viceroy, 1755-1760 (Amarillas)
    - Decreto del Virrey Marques de las Amarillas para que el Coronel D. Diego Ortiz Parrilla establesca el presidio de S. Saba, Mexico., 1756 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      12 p. 31 cm.
  - Provincias Internas, Mexico. Comandante General, 1776-1783 (Croix)
    - LS to Governor of Coahuila, Chihuahua., 1778 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      1 p. 30 cm. Orders Lt. Eugenio Fernandez to command the Presidio at Bahia del Espirito Santo.
  - Ramirez, Pedro.
    - Expediente sobre que paguen diexmos las misiones de Texas., 1781 Mar 17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      8 p. 32 cm. A letter from Ramirez to Gen. Croix, with copy of letter to ecclesias- tical official of tithes.
  - Coahuila, Mexico. Governor, 1777-1783 (Ugalde)
    - Proclamation forbidding export of livestock from the province because of acute shortage, Monclova., 1782 Feb 5
      2 p. 31x43 cm.
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Oversize, Box 5, folder 150.
  - Texas (Province) Gobernador, 1778-1787 (Cabello)
    - [Expediente] Sobre tratantes de la Luisiana para su comercio con los Indios Amigos de Texas., 1784-88 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      108 p. 10-31.5 cm. At head of title: Provincia de Texas. Años de 1784 a 88. Correspondence between the governors of Texas and Louisiana and officials at Nacogdoches and Natchitoches relating to trade with Indians on the Texas border.
  - Texas (Province) Gobernador, 1778-1787 (Cabello)
    - ALS to Jacobo Ugarte y Loyola, Comandante General of the Provincias Internas, Bexar, Texas., 1787 Jan 5 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      6 p. 30 cm. Encloses an account of expenses for presents to Indians.
  - Guerra, Pedro
    - ALS to Miguel José de Emperan, Candela, Coahuila., 1790 Mar 23 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      2, 4, 3 p. 30 cm. Transmitting lists of inhabitants of Candela, their weapons and horses.
  - Nolasco Corrasco, Pedro
    - Relacion que manifiesta la posibilidad, Armas y Caballos que tienen los vecinos agregados a este Presidio de San Juan Baptista del Rio Grande.. ., Presidio de Rio Grande., 1790 Apr 17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      6 p. 30 cm.
  - Barela Bermudez, Franciso
    - Report to Gov. Miguel José de Emperan on the arms and horses at Parras., 1790 Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      2 p. 29 cm.
  - Mascaro, Manuel Agustin
    - ALS to Bernardo Bonavia, Zimapan, Mexico., 1792 Mar 15 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      4 p. col.plan 29 cm. On a bridge to be built at Taxguillo. Includes TLS from Phil Townsend Hanna, "Westways", to H.R. Wagner, Nov 12, 1936, re. publication of the letter and plan in an upcoming issue of "Westways".
  - Flores, Vicente, claimant
    - Expediente promovido por Dn. Vicente Flores sobre Posesion de rancho nombrado Nra. Sa. de los Dolores juez comisndo. el Gobr. de la Prova. de Texas teniente Coronel Dn. Manuel Muñoz., 1792 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      65 numb.l 32 cm.
  - Barela Bermudez, Francisco
    - LS to Intendente of San Luis Potosi, Parras, Coahuila., 1792 Aug 20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      5 p. 30 cm. Asks to be relieved as subdelegado. 2 other documents relating to the request appended.
  - Spain. Sovereigns, etc., 1788-1808 (Charles IV)
    - Copy of royal cedula of Mar. 23, 1798, relating to land grants, promulgated at Monclova December, 1798., 1798 Mar 23 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      2 p. 30 cm.
  - Provincias Internas, Mexico. Comandante General, 1792-1804 (Nava).
    - Order rationing cigarros, Chihuahua., 1800 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      2 p. 32x42 cm.
  - Noticias, Estensas, y Geografia de Nuevo Mexico hechas el año de 1805.
    - Information compiled for the consulate at Vera Cruz. (Box 1, Folder 19)
      67 p. 31 cm. Contains (1) Account of New Mexico (2) Letter 16 Jul 1808 from José María Quiros to Nemesio Salcedo requesting further information (3) Salcedo's answer, dated 1 Sep 1808 (4) Account of Nueva Viscaya (5) Account of Texas by Gov. J.B. Elguezabal (6) Statistics of New Mexico, Coahuila, Texas, and Sonora.
  - Mexico. (Viceroyalty) Laws, statutes, etc.
    - Copy of cedula relating to land grants in the Provincias Internas, Aranjuez., 1805 Feb 14 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      8 p. 32 cm.
  - Spain. Ministerio de Hacienda.
    - Copia de real orden pasada por el ministro de hacienda al intendente del Nuevo Orleans sobre las diferencias ocurridas con los Estados Unidos de America, Aranjuez. (Box 1, Folder 21)
      5 p. 32 cm. Outlines the claims made by Monroe and Pinckney including the boundaries of Louisiana, the breakdown of negotiations, and warns against American hostile action. Signed: Soler, and addressed to Sr. D. Ventura Morales.
  - Expediente sobre ocurrencias de la frontera hasta la retirada a Natchitoches del Exercito Americana 1806. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    18 p. 30 cm. Copy made in 1827 of correspondence in 1806 between Gov. Cordero of Texas and Gen. Wilkinson on question of Texas-Louisiana boundary.
  - Wilkinson, James, 1757-1825.
    - Translation of letter to Gov. Cordero of Texas, Nacogdoches, Texas., 1806? (Box 1, Folder 23)
      3 p. 32 cm. On the Texas-Louisiana boundary question.
  - Spain. Ministerio de Hacienda.
    - Copy of letter to Viceroy of Mexico, Madrid., 1806 Jul 29 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      3 p. 31 cm. Transmits information from Spanish consul at New York on smugglers.
  - Fundacion de la Villa de Palafox, 1809-10 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    50 p. 21-30 cm. Contains original petition of Juan José Dias and official correspon- dence relating to the founding of Palafox, Apr 7, 1809 - Aug 21, 1810.
  - Martinez, Augustin.
    - ALS to Gov. Cordero of Texas, Santa Rosa, Texas., 1811 Jun 16 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      2 p. 21 cm.
  - Provincias Internas, Mexico. Comandante General, 1805-1813 (Salcedo).
    - Declaration of amnesty to parti- cipants in the Hidalgo rebellion, Chihuahua., 1811 Apr 20
      2 p. 44 cm. With endorsements showing publi- cation at Monclova, Santa Rosa, Candela, and other points.
      See: Oversize, Box 5, folder 151.
  - Mexico. (Viceroyalty) Audencia Real.
    - Resolucion de la Real Audencia de Guadalajara sobre la Solicitud hecha por el gobernador de Tejas acerca de que se le concediere facultad para mandar dar azotes., [1812] (Box 1, Folder 27)
      20 p. 15-32 cm. Petition of Gov. Salcedo July 9, 1810, decision of the Audencia Jan 16, 1812, of the royal cedula on which the decision was based, and letters of transmittal.
  - Flores, Tomas
    - Don Tomas Flores, Administrador de Tabacos de Coaguila y Texas, repre- sentando que el Caudillo de los Insurgentes, Pedro Aranda, mando descontar en Riogrande ocho mil pesos que el Fiel de Tabaco de Bexar Suplio de los productos de la renta al Habilitado de aquella compana, solicita su reintegro., [1812] (Box 1, Folder 28)
      39 p. 21-32 cm. Flores' petition and accompanying documents.
  - Ciudad de Bexar. Ano de 1813. Expediente instruido sobre el embargo, avaluo y remate de bienes a los individuos de la misma ciudad que tomaron partido con los insurgentes por una junta formada de orden superior compuesta del Capitan Francisco del Prado, Luis Galan, José Antonio Saucedo. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    124 p. 32 cm. Confiscation of property of those who took part in Hidalgo's revolt against Spain.
  - Ramos Arizpe, Miguel, 1775-1843.
    - Translation of an address presented to the Cortes of Spain in the year 1813 by Doctor Don Miguel Arispe... (Box 2, Folder 30)
      52 p. 24.5 cm. Incomplete. A description of the Provincias Internas. Pub. Cadiz 1812 with title: Memoria que el Doctor D. Miguel Ramos de Ariste .... presenta a el Augusto Congreso ... Cf. Streeter, Bib. of Texas, no 1050.
  - Noticia de la revolucion de la Provincia de Texas., [1813?] (Box 2, Folder 31)
    12 p. 32 cm. A compilation of official docu- ments, with a short introduction, relating to the Gutierrez-Magee expedition.
  - Garza, Ramon de la
    - LS to Comandante General, Provincias internas, Rio Grande., 1818 Mar 3 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Reports the abandonment of the Villa of Palafox.
    - ALS to Comandante General, Provincias internas, Presidio de Rio Grande., 1818 Mar 3 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      6 p. 21 cm.
  - Nava, José María
    - Declaracion tomada al Vecino de Bexar José María Nava que se presente de este punto fugado de la Nacion Comanche, Presidio de Bahia., 1819 Aug 5 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Accompanied by letter of trans- mittal to Governor of Texas and by him to Comandante, Provincias internas.
  - Spain. Sovereigns, etc., 1814-1833. (Ferdinand VII).
    - Copy of Royal order including Englishmen in the amnesty granted to rebels in the Spanish colonies., 1820 Aug 24 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      4 p. 21 cm. Transmitted by Joaquin Arredondo, Comandante General of the Provincias Internas to the Governor of Coahuila, Jan 3, 1821.
  - Provincias Internas de Oriente, Mexico. Comandante General, 1821-1823 (Lopez)
    - LS to Governor of Coahuila, Saltillo., 1821 Nov 3 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      3 p. 21 cm. Transmits copy of Act of Independence of Mexico.
  - Medero, José Francisco.
    - LS to Governor Elozua of Coahuila, Monclova., 1822 Jan 14 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      3 p. 21 cm. On local political affairs.
  - Cuatro Cienegas, Mexico. Ayuntamiento.
    - ALS to Antonio Crespo, Cuatro Cienegas., 1822 Oct 9 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      3 p. 21 cm.
  - Seguin, Erasmo, 1782-1857.
    - Memoria que Don Erasmo Seguin Dipu- tado permanente de la Provincia de Texas, presentio al exmo. sor. Presidente de la Republica Mexicana., 1824 Oct 28 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      13 p. 31 cm. Last leaf torn, interferes with signature. Refers to conditions in the province of Texas and recommends that measures of precaution be taken to safeguard the province.
  - Nuevo Leon, Mexico. Congreso.
    - LS to the Deputies of Coahuila and Texas, Monterrey., 1824 Dec 22 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      2 p. 29 cm. Signed: Juan José de la Garza and Joséph Francisco Arroyos.
  - Austin, Stephen Fuller, 1793-1836.
    - LS to the Governor of the State of Coahuila and Texas, San Felipe de Austin., 1825 Feb 5 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      2 p. 25 cm. Concerned with permission for the inhabitants to export some of their products.
  - Mexico. Secretaría de Relaciones Exteriores.
    - LS to Gobernador de Estados Internos de Oriente, Mexico., 1825 Mar 12 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      4 p. 20 cm. Signed: Alaman. Concerned with immigration restrictions in relation to Great Britain and the U.S.
  - Austin, Stephen Fuller, 1793-1836.
    - LS to Rafael Gonzales, San Felipe de Austin., 1825 Mar 16 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      2 p. 25 cm. "Duplicado" at head of page 1.
  - Coahuila and Texas (State) Gobernador, 1824-1826 (Gonzales).
    - AL to Esteban Austin, Saltillo., 1825 Apr 15 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      3 p. 22 cm. Signed with rubric. Relates to permission for the exportation of goods.
  - Mexico. Secretaría de Relaciones Exteriores.
    - LS to the Governor of the State of Coahuila and Texas, Mexico., 1825 Apr 24 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      2 p. 21 cm. Signed: Alaman. Relates to Austin's petition for a port of entry at Galveston.
  - Coahuila and Texas (State) Gobernador, 1824-1826 (Gonzales).
    - AL to Esteban Austin, n.p., 1825 May 18 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      2 p. 21 cm. Signed with rubric. Discusses the necessity for Political Chief of the Department who resides at Bexar to be given enough money.
    - AL to Esteban Austin, n.p., 1825 May 31 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      1 p. 22 cm. Signed with rubric.
  - Mexico. Consulado. New York.
    - DS to captains of ships bound for Mexico, New York. (Box 2, Folder 48)
      2 p. 24.5 cm. Signed: J. Ignacio de Pasadre. Lists documents required by Mexican customs.
  - Mexico. Secretaría de Relaciones Exteriores.
    - ALS to the Governer of Coahuila and Texas, Mexico., 1825 Jul 23 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      2 p. 20.5 cm. Orders that Richard Raynal Keene not be allowed to enter the country. Signed: Alaman.
    - LS to Governor of Coahuila and Texas, Mexico., 1825 Aug 3 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      2 p. 20.5 cm. At top: Reservado. On allowing U.S. citizens to settle in the prohibited frontier areas.
    - ALS to the Governor of Coahuila and Texas, Mexico., 1825 Sep 9 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      3 p. 20 cm. Signed: Alaman
  - Coahuila and Texas (State) Secretaría.
    - Letters, signed, to the Governor of the State of Coahuila and Texas, Saltillo., 1825 Dec 9 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      2 items. 30 cm. Signed: El Baron de Bastrop y Maríano Varela. Relate to the new laws proposed by the Ayuntamiento. Accompanied by a list of expedientes (1 p.).
  - Mexico. Comision de Limites.
    - Instruccion de D. Pedro Simon del Campo Secretario que fue de ambar comands de la de Oriente y Occidente., 1825 Dec 6 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      3 items. 21 cm. Inventories of armaments at Bejar, Bahia del Espiritu Santo and Parron, 1825 Oct 30, copied at Saltillo, 1825 Nov 14, with letter of transmittal 1825 Dec 6, signed by Mateo Ahumada.
  - U.S. Legation. Spain.
    - Copy of a letter to the Duque del Infantado Principal Secretary of State, Madrid., 1826 Jan 20 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      57 p. 32 cm. "Confidential" at head of page 1. Discusses Spain's recognition of Mexico's independence.
  - Austin, Stephen Fuller, 1793-1836.
    - Report of strength and armament of the militia at San Felipe de Austin, San Felipe de Austin., 1826 Jun 14 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      1p. 21.5x33.5 cm. Signed: Estevan F. (Stephen Fuller) Austin.
  - Sepulveda, José Antonio.
    - Report on the militia company at Nacogdoches, Texas, Nacogdoches., 1826 Aug 4 (Box 2, Folder 56)
      1p. 34 cm. Signed: José Antonio Sepulveda. Certified by Samuel Norris.
  - Austin, Stephen Fuller, 1793-1836.
    - Copy of LS to José Antonio Saucedo, San Felipe de Austin, Texas., 1826 Aug 11 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      2 p. 23 cm. Transmits a request for permission to organize a militia company at Nacogdoches.
    - LS to Victor Blanco, San Felipe de Austin, Texas., 1826 Oct 24 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      4 p. 23.5 cm A reponse to the accusations of James Gaines concerning Austin's interference in the formation of a militia.
    - Copy of Report to the Congress of the State of Coahuila and Texas, n.p., 1826 Nov 20 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      7 p. 31 cm. "Es copia: J. Antonio Padilla" Ideas pertaining to the intro- duction of slaves into the new colonies.
  - U.S. Dept. of State.
    - Draft of a report on the Panama Congress, n.p., [1826?] (Box 2, Folder 60)
      4 p. 25 cm. Signed: H. Clay
  - Coahuila and Texas (State) Gobernador, 1827-1831 (Viesca).
    - Draft of LS to Stephen F. Austin, n.p., 1827 Mar 7 (Box 2, Folder 61)
      1 p. 30 cm. Signed with rubric. The government is satisfied with Austin's conduct and good faith.
  - San Antonio, Texas. Ayuntamiento.
    - LS to Comandante General, Coahuila and Texas, San Fernando de Bexar., 1827 Oct 25 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      3 p. 33 cm. and enclosures 13 p. 20-33 cm. Protests closing of San Bernardo Bay as a port of entry, and encloses copies of previous orders and correspondence on the subject.
  - Austin, Stephen Fuller, 1793-1836.
    - ALS to Governor of Coahuila and Texas, Saltillo, Mexico., 1827 Nov 6 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      4 p. 30 cm. On the system of government in Austin's colony.
    - ALS to Governor of Coahuila and Texas, Saltillo, Mexico., 1827 Nov 14 (Box 2, Folder 64)
      3 p. 27.5 cm. On cost of sealed paper.
  - Coahuila and Texas (State) Gobernador, 1827-1831 (Viesca).
    - Draft of a letter to Stephen F. Austin, n.p., 1827 Nov 21 (Box 2, Folder 65)
      1 p. 30 cm. Signed with rubric.
  - Bustamente, Anastasio, Pres. Mexico, 1780-1853.
    - ALS to Manuel Mier y Teran, Matamoros, Mexico., 1828 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 66)
      4 p. 30 cm. Signed with rubric. Encloses copy of pay roll for offi- cers of the boundary commission.
  - Courier del Natchitoches de Julio 23 1828., 1828 Jul 23 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    5 p. 30 cm. Translations of excerpts from the Courier of June 16 and July 23, 1828, relating to Texas.
  - Bradburn, Juan Davis.
    - LS to Manuel de Mier y Teran, Matamoros, Mexico., 1828 Nov 22 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      4 p. 32 cm. On p. 4 is a draft of a reply.
  - Mexico (Republic). Secretaría de la Defensa Nacional.
    - Informe Sre. seis cartas de Tejas y en la particular de la Bahia de Galveston y la posicion de un fuerte en la isla, Soto la Marina., 1829 (Box 2, Folder 69)
      13 p. 30 cm. Title from docket. Copy of a letter to Felipe de la Garza on the subject of a fort at Galveston Bay. Enclosed: copy of reports from Juan Nunez and Alejandro Thompson of the Mexican Navy, and a copy of a letter from Felipe de la Garza to the Secretaría de Guerra y Marina. With letter of transmittal from Felipe de la Garza to Manuel de Mier y Teran.
  - Monterrey, Mexico. Diputacion Permanente.
    - Proyeto de la diputacion permante. de Monterrey concernte. a la conservacion y mas facil defensa de Tejas, Monterrey, Mexico., 1829 Aug 28 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      3 p. 30.5 cm. Title from docket.
  - Kimble, Helena (Gimlech) Dill.
    - Petition for confirmation of title to land, Nacogdoches, Texas., 1830 Mar 15 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      6 p. 30 cm. Accompanied by affirmatory order of the Governor of Coahuila and Texas.
  - Arciniega, Miguel.
    - Testimonial for José Antonio Farias, Bejar., 1830 Jul 1 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      Signed: Miguel Arciniega, Juan Xavier Busti, and Ygnacio Arocha.
    - Testimonials for Ygnacio de Leon and José Gomez, Bejar, Texas., 1830 Jul 22 (Box 2, Folder 73)
      4 p. 31 cm.
  - Poblacion que tiene el Estado de Tamaulipas segun los census particu- lares ultimos de cada pueblo, Victoria., 1830 Nov 10 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    2 p. 29.5 cm. Signed: Manuel Garza de Porras.
  - Bradburn, Juan Davis.
    - LS to Manuel de Mier y Teran, Galveston, Texas., 1831 Jan 24 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      4 p. 32 cm. Copy, transcription, and translation available. See Series II, Box 4, folder 142.
  - San Antonio, Texas. Jefe Politico.
    - Copy of letter to Antonio Elozua, Comandante of San Antonio, Bexar, Texas., 1831 Feb 27 (Box 2, Folder 76)
      4 p. 32 cm. Concerns the disagreement between J.F. Madero, land commissioner, and J.D. Bradburn, Comandante at Anahuac. Signed: Ramon Musquiz Transcription and translation available. See Series II, Box 4, folder 143.
  - Kimble, Helena (Gimlech) Dill.
    - ADS, Nacogdoches, Texas., 1831 Mar 7 (Box 2, Folder 77)
      4 p. 30.5 cm. Signed: Helena Gimlech and witnessed by Manuel de los Santos Coy and two others. Petition is regard to a land title.
  - Degollado y Villaseñor, Faustino.
    - ADS, Matamoros, Mexico., 1831 May 2 (Box 2, Folder 78)
      2 p. 32 cm. Statement of his services in the war for independence, including service under Gen. Mina.
  - Bradburn, Juan Davis.
    - LS to Manuel de Mier y Teran, Galveston, 1831 June (Box 2, Folder 79)
      4 p. 31.5 cm. Discusses Austin's opposition to Article 9 of the Law of April 6, 1830.
  - [Guerra, Juan].
    - AL (Copy) to Ministro de Relaciones, n.p., 1831 Aug 14 (Box 2, Folder 80)
      7 p. 31 cm. Signed: J.G. On irregularities in the recent elections in Victoria, Tamaulipas.
  - San Antonio, Texas. Jefe Politico.
    - Expediente relativo al numero de familias introducida para el Empresario ... Estevan F. Austin..., Bexar and San Felipe de Austin, Texas., 1831 Sep 12 (Box 3, Folder 81)
      21 p. 33 cm. Dated 1831 Sep 12 - Oct 27. Signed: Ramon Musquiz, F.W. Johnson, Miguel Arciniega, Walter C. White, Samuel M. Williams.
    - Estadistica del Departamento de Texas, San Fernando de Bexar., 1831 Oct 10 (Box 3, Folder 82)
      5 p. 32 cm. Signed: Ramon Musquiz.
    - LS to Governer of Coahuila and Texas, Bejar, Texas., 1831 Nov 19 (Box 3, Folder 83)